Lucas Lange

RESEARCH ASSISTANT · PHD CANDIDATE

■ lange@informatik.uni-leipzig.de | 🔏 lucaslange.de | 🖸 luckyos-code | 🛅 lucaslange

Summary_

I am currently working and teaching as a research assistant while pursuing a PhD in computer science. My research interests align with the common border between data science, machine learning, and privacy - leading me to the topic of "Privacy-Preserving Data Analysis (Machine Learning)". An environment of diverse knowledge exchange is essential to me, fueling the agile prototyping approach I like to adopt when testing hypotheses in my experiments.

Experience

Leipzig University

Leipzig, Germany

RESEARCH ASSISTANT (WISSENSCHAFTLICHER MITARBEITER)

Mar. 2022 - Present

- Research in "Privacy-Preserving Data Analysis (Machine Learning)" as a PhD candidate.
- Conducting and supervising computer science courses at Leipzig University, especially in the field of databases and data science (tutorials, labs, seminars, lectures).
- Skills: Deep Learning · Data Science · Data Privacy · Research.

ScaDS.Al Dresden/Leipzig Leipzig, Germany

RESEARCH ASSISTANT (WISSENSCHAFTLICHER MITARBEITER)

Mar. 2022 - Present

• Within the scope of my position as a PhD candidate at Leipzig University.

InfAI - Institute for Applied Informatics

Leipzig, Germany

RESEARCH ASSISTANT (WHK)

Oct. 2019 - Feb. 2020

- Working individually on the ShapBiRd project, an effort to create a linked data infrastructure and workflow for the institute's bibliography.
 github.com/AKSW/shapbird
- Skills: Python · Docker · Semantic Web

eccenca GmbH Leipzig, Germany

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER Jun. 2018 - Apr. 2019

- Visual Editor Based on SHACL Shapes (Bachelor Thesis).
- Specification and implementation of a visual editor for linked data knowledge graphs furthermore, adjustable to specific domains by utilizing SHACL shape descriptions.
- Skills: JavaScript · React.js · Semantic Web

InfAI - Institute for Applied Informatics

Leipzig, Germany

STUDENT ASSISTANT (SHK)

Jul. 2017 - Apr. 2018

- Lead an agile software engineering student project at Leipzig University.
 github.com/AKSW/Auto-Slides
- Tutored an agile software engineering student project at Leipzig University.
- Skills: Agile Project Management · JavaScript · Java · Semantic Web

Education

Leipzig University

Leipzig, Germany

PHD IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

Mar. 2022 - Present

• Topic: Privacy-Preserving Data Analysis (Machine Learning).

Leipzig University

Leipzig, Germany

M.Sc. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

Apr. 2019 - Jan. 2022

- Thesis: Privacy-Preserving Detection of COVID-19 in X-Ray Images.

Université Grenoble Alpes (UGA)

Grenoble, France

Erasmus+—M.Sc. in Computer Science Sep. 2020 - Jun. 2021

• Courses in Machine Learning and Robotics.

Leipzig University

Leipzig, Germany

B.Sc. in Computer Science Oct. 2015 - Mar. 2019

Thesis: Visual Editor Based on SHACL Shapes.

Projects

DP-X-COVIDScaDS.Al Dresden/Leipzig

☑ GITHUB.COM/LUCKYOS-CODE/DP-X-COVID

- Privacy-Preserving Detection of COVID-19 in X-Ray Images (Master Thesis).
- The goal of this work was to implement a private image classifier for COVID-19 X-ray images. The model was trained by applying privacy-preserving machine learning procedures to achieve a differentially private model and thus preventing attacks from causing data leakage.
- Skills: Deep Learning (CNNs), Data Privacy (DP-SGD, PATE), Python, Tensorflow/Keras

X-COVID

GITHUB.COM/LUCKYOS-CODE/X-COVID

- Detection of COVID-19 in X-ray images.
- Binary (COVID-19 vs. normal): 97.8%, Multiclass (COVID-19 vs. Pneumonia vs. Normal): 94.1%
- Skills: Deep Learning (CNNs), Python, Tensorflow/Keras

SentArg

☑ GITHUB.COM/LUCKYOS-CODE/ARGU

- Argument retrieval model for Touché @ CLEF 2020 1st Shared Task on Argument Retrieval.
- The task was to retrieve and rank arguments from the provided dataset of crawled content from online debate portals for 50 given topics—covering a wide range of controversial issues. We tried to improve our model by factoring sentiment analysis into the ranking scheme.
- Skills: Google Cloud Computing, Deep Learning (NLP), Docker, Python

Publications

SentArg: A Hybrid Doc2Vec/DPH Model with Sentiment Analysis Refinement

CHRISTIAN STAUDTE AND LUCAS LANGE, IN: CLEF 2020 WORKING NOTES

% ceur-ws.org/Vol-2696/paper_191.pdf

Further Education _____

2021	Fundamentals of Neuroscience Part 1, HarvardX	edX
2020	Deep Learning Specialization, deeplearning.ai	Coursera
2020	Machine Learning, Stanford Online	Coursera
2020	Blockchain A-Z™: Learn How To Build Your First Blockchain, SuperDataScience	Udemy
2020	TRIZ User (Level 1), Target Invention	TRIZ-Trainer

Personal

Languages	German Native, English B2/C1, French B1/B2
Hobbies	Fitness, Reading, Hiking, Travel, Cinema

Interests Deep Learning, Data Privacy & Ethics, Data Science, Environmental Issues, Medicine